A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, general correspondence, RG 2, 1947-1951 FA759
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, general correspondence, RG 2, 1947-1951
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
FA759
88 Cubic Feet standard document boxes, 352-548, 562-563 (Stack Material)
Biographical / Historical
Rockefeller Foundation general correspondence:
The existence of a separate General Correspondence file is in part a result of the reorganization in 1927-1928 of the various philanthropic boards founded by the Rockefeller Family. The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial consolidated with the Foundation; some of its programs emerged in the Division of Social Sciences. The humanities interests of the General Education Board were taken over by the Foundation and provided a basis for the Foundation's new Division of Humanities. The International Health Board was reorganized and renamed the International Health Division.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence of The Rockefeller Foundation consists principally of material not directly connected with an institutional grant. It includes: inter-office memoranda, correspondence between field officers and the home office, extracts from officers' diaries, forms and other material relating to fellowships; casual requests for information, employment, or aid; printed matter and letters of abuse received by the Foundation. As such, the General Correspondence provides insight into the day-to-day workings of the Foundation.
Programs other than public health are not amply represented in the early portion of the General Correspondence. Material on the Division of Humanities and the Division of Social Sciences is especially scanty before 1935. After 1940, the volume of this material increases steadily. Indeed, the General Correspondence files as a whole are relatively compact up to 1940; after 1941, they expand enormously.
Some of the most important features and subjects of these files are as follows:
100: STAFF COMMUNICATIONS AND INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS
This designation applies to two distinct types of documents.
(1) STAFF COMMUNICATIONS. Much of the material under this heading consists of correspondence between or regarding staff officers (eg. a field officer and a member of the home office staff), or gives details of employment and assignment of the field officer. Thus this file is in the nature of a supplement of the Foundation's personnel records. Correspondence between retirees and active staff members is often also filed under this designation, under the names of the individuals. One will also find here inter-office correspondence from the New York headquarters. Of special interest in this connection are the memos of Raymond B. Fosdick (President of the Rockefeller Foundation, 1936-1948), which usually consist of several folders for each year indicated. Some correspondence with trustees, especially Thomas B. Debevoise, may also be found here.
(2) INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS. Correspondence between The Rockefeller Foundation and the League of Nations (especially with Arthur Sweetser) lodges under this heading and persists into the 1940s. After the establishment of the United Nations Organization in 1944/5, documentation of the Foundation's cooperation with various U.N. efforts is to be found. Of special interest are the files regarding Selskar M. Gunn and Warren Weaver's service with UNRRA (1944-1946) and John Marshall's presence as an observer at the earliest organizational meetings of UNESCO (1946-1947).
200: THE UNITED STATES (201-258: Individual States and Territories)
The largest concentration of material is to be found under this designation. It is also the most miscellaneous in character. Correspondence ranges from communications with Federal agencies and departments, to letters of advice, records of interviews, appeals for aid, employment inquiries, and crank mail.
The vast bulk of these files dating between 1927 and 1939 relates to the work of the International Health Division, supplementing material previously processed as RG 5. This includes material on grants to state boards of health, training grants for public health personnel at stations in Ohio or Mississippi, and advice on administrative matters. Following the practice of the IHD, most of these earlier files were arranged under an individual state heading rather than under that of the nation as a whole. By 1935 most of the IHD activities had declined as funding became available to the states through the Federal government for this purpose. Correspondence with the individual state agencies shrank accordingly. The advisory functions of the IHD thereafter took place mainly in the form of pooling information (and occasionally personnel) with the U.S. Public Health Service.
Those states files which remain sizeable after 1935 (such as 216: Illinois-University of Chicago, and 248: Tennessee: TVA) do not relate primarily to IHD activities. In 1951, the use of state numbers in filing was almost totally abandoned.
200: UNITED STATES PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE
During World War II, the Foundation maintained close ties with USPHS, as reflected in the large file of correspondence between Foundation officers and various USPHS officials. This file refers particularly to the Foundation's effort to provide yellow fever vaccine to the Armed Forces. Also of interest for this period is a set of weekly reports on the incidence of virulent disease (plague, smallpox, etc.) around the world.
200E: FELLOWSHIPS
The earlier portion of material so designated (through 1935) is taken up with grants for training public health personnel as requested by various state boards of health. It thus amplifies the documentation of IHD activities noted above. This material includes both declinations as well as acceptances.
Similar material through the 1930s is to be found under 200S: Social Science Research Council, consisting mostly of application forms and correspondence concerning potential SSRC grantees.
For the years 1945-46, an extensive file of Postwar Fellowships follows the regular fellowship file in the General Correspondence. While the character of Foundation support of these Fellows is unclear, the advisory function of Foundation officers in their selection and placement is amply documented here.
300-833: INDIVIDUAL NATIONAL FILES
The files under this heading include administrative and budgetary material for field offices, reports of interviews with potential grantees, governmental and educational figures, diary extracts (usually travel notes, sometimes quite extensive), and miscellaneous correspondence with private and public scientific or cultural institutions and individuals. The majority of this material (especially before 1935) continues the records of the IHD in its international program (see RG 5), and deals primarily with public health programs and medical training. After 1935, the subject matter in the files becomes more diversified.
Scattered throughout these series are observations by Foundation officers on the political and social climate around the world. The Rockefeller Foundation maintained political neutrality regarding the internal affairs of host countries, and cooperated closely with governmental ministries and state-controlled universities -- especially in the areas of public health and the social sciences. Nevertheless, a close watch was kept on developments affecting intellectual freedom and the general climate of cooperation which the Foundation saw as the main prerequisite for performing or sponsoring significant work. This is reflected in the General Correspondence files, where one may find contemporary eyewitness reports and informed outside opinions on such phenomena of this century as the development of Fascism in Europe, the growth of Communism in eastern Europe and China, and the rise or fall of various dictatorships in Latin America.
Large quantities of material may be found under the following headings:
300: South America 315: Cuba 400: Great Britain 427: Canada 437: Jamaica 464: India (including 464.1: Mysore and 464.5: Travancore, through 1944) 500: France 601: China 700: Europe
The bulk of these files indicates either high levels of Foundation activity or the presence of a field office in the country concerned, and thus an "Administration" file will be found here as well as material filed alphabetically or under a program letter. Special features include the 1945-46, 500E file (France-Government Fellowships), which consist of material similar to that described under 200E for the same period. Under 700, one will also find material on the Paris Field Office supplementing that processed separately as RG 6.1.
SPECIAL TOPIC: REFUGEE SCHOLARS, 1933-1946
The General Correspondence contains a mass of material on the plight of European scholars deprived of means or work by the rise of Fascism. This material is similar and supplementary to that found in RG 1 under the same heading. Most of the material in the General Correspondence bearing on this topic may be found as listed below:
717: Germany--Refugee Scholars, 1933-1939 789: Poland-----Refugee Scholars, 1936-1939 200: U.S.---------Refugee Scholars, 1940-1945
These files generally fall into two parts:
(1) A chronological file entitled "Exiled Scholars" which consists of officer's correspondence, diary extracts, lists of exiled academics compiled from various sources, correspondence with various committees and institutions engaged in placing these scholars, and copies of the minutes of those committees with which The Rockefeller Foundation cooperated most closely.
(2) An alphabetical file of correspondence with or concerning individual scholars whose placement the Foundation sponsored or financed in part.
(3) Much material filed under 700: Europe and individual European country numbers (including 400: Great Britain, and 805: Turkey) during the period 1933-1945 also deals with this topic.
Arrangement
The RF General Correspondence is arranged into Subgroups by Year of correspondence.
The original filing system has been retained.
Each Subgroup/Year is comprised of Series (a geographic-numeric numeric number assigned to each country, state, and/or geographic region) and Subseries (A letter designating the Program/Project area.)
General files within each series are not assinged a program letter.
Important irregularities in the original filing order are noted below:
(1) Series 100: International files are strictly alphabetical until 1941; after 1941, miscellaneous A-Z files are maintained containing small amounts of material on individuals. These immediately follow the main Series 100 International file.
(2) Correspondence with various state boards of public health precede the alphabetical file for each state or territory of the United States (201-258).
(3) Administration files for RF field offices precede the alphabetical file for the country in which they were established.
Conditions Governing Access
Records are open for scholarly research.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Related Materials
Subjects documented in the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial records, the General Education Board records and the International Health Board/Division (Rockefeller Foundation records, Record Group 5) is continued in the RF General Correspondence -- particularly in the case of the International Health Board.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence include:
FA758 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1940-1946
FA308 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1924-1939
FA425 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1952-1957
FA400 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1958-1970
FA401 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1971-1980
FA402 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1981-1990
Rockefeller Foundation
- General Correspondence, 1947
  - International, 1947; 02.1947/100
    - Staff - International - Aitken, Thomas H. G. - Anderson, Charles R., 1947 (Box 352, Folder 2383)
    - Staff - International - Anderson, R. K., 1947 (Box 352, Folder 2384)
    - Staff - International - Balfour, M. C. - 1, 1947 (Box 352, Folder 2385)
    - Staff - International - Balfour, M. C. - 2, 1947 (Box 353, Folder 2386)
    - Staff - International - (Bar-Bel), 1947 (Box 353, Folder 2387)
    - Staff - International - Bevier, George, 1947 (Box 353, Folder 2388)
    - Staff - International - Buchanan, Norman S., 1947 (Box 353, Folder 2389)
    - Staff - International - Bugher, John C. - Burden, Robert P., 1947 (Box 353, Folder 2390)
    - Staff - International - Carr, Henry P., 1947 (Box 353, Folder 2391)
    - Staff - International - Carr, Henry P., 1947 (Box 354, Folder 2392)
    - Staff - International - Carr, Henry P., 1947 (Box 354, Folder 2393)
    - Staff - International - Carter, J.C. - Causey, O.R., 1947 (Box 354, Folder 2394)
    - Staff - International - (Ch-Da), 1947 (Box 354, Folder 2395)
    - Staff - International - Debevoise, Thomas M. - Diplomatic Service, 1947 (Box 354, Folder 2396)
    - Staff - International - Dyer, Brian R., 1947 (Box 354, Folder 2397)
    - Staff - International - Elmendorf, John E., 1947 (Box 355, Folder 2398)
    - Staff - International - Evans, Roger F., 1947 (Box 355, Folder 2399)
    - Staff - International - Fahs, Charles B., 1947 (Box 355, Folder 2400)
    - Staff - International - Fosdick, Raymond B., 1947 (Box 355, Folder 2401)
    - Staff - International - Fosdick, Raymond B. - Memos - 1-2, 1947 (Box 355, Folder 2402)
    - Staff - International - Fosdick, Raymond B. - Memos - 1-2, 1947 (Box 355, Folder 2403)
    - Staff - International - Fox, John P., 1947 (Box 355, Folder 2404)
    - Staff - International - Grant, John B. - 1-2, 1947 (Box 355, Folder 2405)
    - Staff - International - Grant, John B. - 1-2, 1947 (Box 355, Folder 2406)
    - Staff - International - Grant, John B. - 3-5, 1947 (Box 356, Folder 2407)
    - Staff - International - Grant, John B. - 3-5, 1947 (Box 356, Folder 2408)
    - Staff - International - Grant, John B. - 3-5, 1947 (Box 356, Folder 2409)
    - Staff - International - Goodner, Kenneth - Gregg, Alan, 1947 (Box 356, Folder 2410)
    - Staff - International - Hackett, Lewis W., 1947 (Box 356, Folder 2411)
    - Staff - International - Hackett, Lewis W., 1947 (Box 356, Folder 2412)
    - Staff - International - Hahn, Richard G., 1947 (Box 356, Folder 2413)
    - Staff - International - Hayes, Guy S., 1947 (Box 357, Folder 2414)
    - Staff - International - Hill, Rolla B., 1947 (Box 357, Folder 2415)
    - Staff - International - Hirst, Esther Mary - Hirst, George K., 1947 (Box 357, Folder 2416)
    - Staff - International - Hughes, Thomas P. - Information Exchange, 1947 (Box 357, Folder 2417)
    - Staff - International - International - (A-Z), 1947 (Box 357, Folder 2418)
    - Staff - International - Janney, John H., 1947 (Box 357, Folder 2419)
    - Staff - International - Johnson, H.N. - Kendrick, J.F., 1947 (Box 358, Folder 2420)
    - Staff - International - Kerr, J. Austin, 1947 (Box 358, Folder 2421)
    - Staff - International - Kerr, J. Austin, 1947 (Box 358, Folder 2422)
    - Staff - International - Kitchen, S.F., 1947 (Box 358, Folder 2423)
    - Staff - International - Kittredge, Tracy B. - Lambert S.M., 1947 (Box 358, Folder 2424)
    - Staff - International - Leach, Charles N., 1947 (Box 358, Folder 2425)
    - Staff - International - Leach, Charles N., 1947 (Box 358, Folder 2426)
    - Staff - International - Lennett, E.H. - Logan, John A., 1947 (Box 358, Folder 2427)
    - Staff - International - McCoy, O.R., 1947 (Box 359, Folder 2428)
    - Staff - International - McIntosh, W.A., 1947 (Box 359, Folder 2429)
    - Staff - International - Magoon, E.H. - Mailing lists, 1947 (Box 359, Folder 2430)
    - Staff - International - Maier, John, 1947 (Box 359, Folder 2431)
    - Staff - International - Maier, John, 1947 (Box 359, Folder 2432)
    - Staff - International - Mann, Albert R., 1947 (Box 359, Folder 2433)
    - Staff - International - Milam, D. Frank, 1947 (Box 359, Folder 2434)
    - Staff - International - Miller, N.M. - Mosely, Philip, 1947 (Box 360, Folder 2435)
    - Staff - International - Noll, Anna Mary - Payne, Janet M., 1947 (Box 360, Folder 2436)
    - Staff - International - Paul, J. Harland, 1947 (Box 360, Folder 2437)
    - Staff - International - Payne, George C., 1947 (Box 360, Folder 2438)
    - Staff - International - Peterson, Osler L., 1947 (Box 360, Folder 2439)
    - Staff - International - Plague, 1947 (Box 360, Folder 2440)
    - Staff - International - Pomerat, Gerald R. - Putnam, Persis - Rickard, E.R., 1947 (Box 361, Folder 2441)
    - Staff - International - Russell, Paul K., 1947 (Box 361, Folder 2442)
    - Staff - International - Russell, Paul K., 1947 (Box 361, Folder 2443)
    - Staff - International - Smith, Hugh S., 1947 (Box 361, Folder 2444)
    - Staff - International - Smithburn, Kenneth C., 1947 (Box 361, Folder 2445)
    - Staff - International - Soper, Fred L. - Stevens, David H., 1947 (Box 361, Folder 2446)
    - Staff - International - Strode, George K., 1947 (Box 361, Folder 2447)
    - Staff - International - Taylor, Richard M., 1947 (Box 361, Folder 2448)
    - Staff - International - Tennant, Mary Elizabeth, 1947 (Box 362, Folder 2449)
    - Staff - International - Tennant, Mary Elizabeth, 1947 (Box 362, Folder 2450)
    - Staff - International - Theiler, Max, 1947 (Box 362, Folder 2451)
    - Staff - International - United Nations, 1947 (Box 362, Folder 2452)
    - Staff - International - UNESCO, 1947 (Box 362, Folder 2453)
    - Staff - International - UNESCO - (A-F), 1947 (Box 362, Folder 2454)
    - Staff - International - UNESCO - Fellowships, 1947 (Box 362, Folder 2455)
    - Staff - International - UNESCO - (G-Z), 1947 (Box 363, Folder 2456)
    - Staff - International - United Nations - World Health Organization, 1947 (Box 363, Folder 2457)
    - Staff - International - Varley, Margaret L., 1947 (Box 363, Folder 2458)
    - Staff - International - Warren, Andrew J., 1947 (Box 363, Folder 2459)
    - Staff - International - Watson, Robert B., 1947 (Box 363, Folder 2460)
    - Staff - International - Watson, Robert B., 1947 (Box 363, Folder 2461)
    - Staff - International - Weaver, Warren, 1947 (Box 363, Folder 2462)
    - Staff - International - Weir, John M., 1947 (Box 364, Folder 2463)
    - Staff - International - Weir, John M., 1947 (Box 364, Folder 2464)
    - Staff - International - Welles, C.W., 1947 (Box 364, Folder 2465)
    - Staff - International - (Wh-Wi), 1947 (Box 364, Folder 2466)
    - Staff - International - Wilson, D. Bruce, 1947 (Box 364, Folder 2467)
    - Staff - International - Worth, C. Brooke, 1947 (Box 364, Folder 2468)
    - Staff - International - Miscellaneous - (A-Z), 1947 (Box 365, Folder 2469)
    - Staff - International - Miscellaneous - (A-Z), 1947 (Box 365, Folder 2470)
    - Staff - International - Miscellaneous - (A-Z), 1947 (Box 365, Folder 2471)
  - International - Nursing, 1947; 02.1947/100.C
    - 100 - C-T Staff - International - C, 1947 (Box 365, Folder 2472)
  - International - Malaria, 1947; 02.1947/100.I
    - 100 - C-T Staff - International - I, 1947 (Box 365, Folder 2472)
  - International - Yellow Fever, 1947; 02.1947/100.O
    - 100 - C-T Staff - International - O, 1947 (Box 365, Folder 2472)
  - International - Humanities and Arts, 1947; 02.1947/100.R
    - 100 - C-T Staff - International - R, 1947 (Box 365, Folder 2472)
  - International - Social Sciences, 1947; 02.1947/100.S
    - 100 - C-T Staff - International - S, 1947 (Box 365, Folder 2472)
  - International - Tuberculosis, 1947; 02.1947/100.T
    - 100 - C-T Staff - International - T, 1947 (Box 365, Folder 2472)
  - United States of America, 1947; 02.1947/200
    - United States - (A-American C), 1947 (Box 365, Folder 2473)
    - United States - (American D-M), 1947 (Box 365, Folder 2474)
    - United States - (American N-Z), 1947 (Box 366, Folder 2475)
    - United States - (An-Ce), 1947 (Box 366, Folder 2476)
    - United States - (An-Ce), 1947 (Box 366, Folder 2477)
    - United States - (An-Ce), 1947 (Box 366, Folder 2478)
    - United States - (An-Ce), 1947 (Box 366, Folder 2479)
    - United States - (An-Ce), 1947 (Box 366, Folder 2480)
    - United States - (Ch-Cl), 1947 (Box 367, Folder 2481)
    - United States - (Co-Cop), 1947 (Box 367, Folder 2482)
    - United States - Cornell University - (A-Z), 1947 (Box 367, Folder 2483)
    - United States - (Cou-Dz), 1947 (Box 367, Folder 2484)
    - United States - (E-F), 1947 (Box 367, Folder 2485)
    - United States - (E-F), 1947 (Box 367, Folder 2486)
    - United States - (Ga-Gh), 1947 (Box 368, Folder 2487)
    - United States - (Gi-Go), 1947 (Box 368, Folder 2488)
    - United States - Grabbe, Paul - Booklet, 1947 (Box 368, Folder 2489)
    - United States - (Gr-Gz), 1947 (Box 368, Folder 2490)
    - United States - (Ha), 1947 (Box 368, Folder 2491)
    - United States - Harvard University - (A-C), 1947 (Box 368, Folder 2492)
    - United States - Harvard University, 1947 (Box 369, Folder 2493)
    - United States - (Har-He), 1947 (Box 369, Folder 2494)
    - United States - (Hi-Hz), 1947 (Box 369, Folder 2495)
    - United States - (I-K), 1947 (Box 369, Folder 2496)
    - United States - (I-K), 1947 (Box 369, Folder 2497)
    - United States - (I-K), 1947 (Box 369, Folder 2498)
    - United States - (L-Li), 1947 (Box 370, Folder 2499)
    - United States - (Lo-Lz), 1947 (Box 370, Folder 2500)
    - United States - (Ma), 1947 (Box 370, Folder 2501)
    - United States - (Me-Mz), 1947 (Box 370, Folder 2502)
    - United States - (National A-Z), 1947 (Box 370, Folder 2503)
    - United States - (Ne-Pa), 1947 (Box 370, Folder 2504)
    - United States - (Pe-Pr), 1947 (Box 371, Folder 2505)
    - United States - Princeton - (A-Z), 1947 (Box 371, Folder 2506)
    - United States - Princeton - Bicentennial Conferences, 1947 (Box 371, Folder 2507)
    - United States - Princeton - Bicentennial Conferences, 1947 (Box 371, Folder 2508)
    - United States - Princeton - Bicentennial Conferences, 1947 (Box 371, Folder 2509)
    - United States - Princeton - Bicentennial Conferences, 1947 (Box 372, Folder 2510)
    - United States - (Pr-Pz), 1947 (Box 372, Folder 2511)
    - United States - (Q-R), 1947 (Box 372, Folder 2512)
    - United States - (Sa-Se), 1947 (Box 372, Folder 2513)
    - United States - (Sf-Ste), 1947 (Box 372, Folder 2514)
    - United States - (Sti-Sz), 1947 (Box 372, Folder 2515)
    - United States - (T-Un), 1947 (Box 373, Folder 2516)
    - United States - (United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration), 1947 (Box 373, Folder 2517)
    - United States - United Service to China, Inc., 1947 (Box 373, Folder 2518)
    - United States - (US: A-T), 1947 (Box 373, Folder 2519)
    - United States - (US: Publc Health Service - Scientific Research Fund), 1947 (Box 373, Folder 2520)
    - United States - United States: State Department, 1947 (Box 373, Folder 2520A)
    - United States - (Un-V), 1947 (Box 374, Folder 2521)
    - United States - (Wa-We, 1947 (Box 374, Folder 2522)
  - United States of America - Medical Sciences, 1947; 02.1947/200.A
    - United States - (A-M), 1947 (Box 374, Folder 2524)
    - United States - (N-Z), 1947 (Box 374, Folder 2525)
  - United States of America - Nursing, 1947; 02.1947/200.C
    - United States, 1947 (Box 374, Folder 2526)
  - United States of America - Natural Sciences and Agriculture, 1947; 02.1947/200.D